<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: icwe | Tomasz Pluskiewicz]]></title>
  <link href="http://t-code.pl/blog/categories/icwe/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://t-code.pl/"/>
  <updated>2021-03-28T12:28:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://t-code.pl/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tomasz Pluskiewicz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lest I forget&#58; International Conference on Web Engineering - Day 2 Research Tracks]]></title>
    <link href="http://t-code.pl/blog/2016/06/ICWE-2016-day-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-19T22:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://t-code.pl/blog/2016/06/ICWE-2016-day-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this week I shortly wrote about the first day Research Track at <a href="http://icwe2016.inf.usi.ch">International Conference on Web Engineering</a> 
which took place between June 6-7. Today it’s time for day 2 (keynote included).</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="day-2">Day 2</h2>

<p>The second day ended with a lovely dinner in the restaurant and lookout point atop <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monte_Br%C3%A8">Monte Brè</a>. Although the weather
was a little flaky, everyone got a chance for some pictures of Lugano from above. Here’s my panorama shot of Lugano:</p>

<p><a href="/uploads/2016/06/lugano_pano_big.jpg"><img src="/uploads/2016/06/lugano_pano.jpg" alt="Lugano panorama" /></a></p>

<p>Other than that, unsurprisingly, the conference research track featured a whole lot of interesting lectures, ideas and
showcases.</p>

<h3 id="the-keynote---microservices---the-hunting-of-the-snark">The keynote - Microservices - The Hunting of the Snark</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/profiles/james-lewis">James Lewis of ThoughtWorks</a> (yes, the one famous for Martin Fowler)
gave and extensive and wildly interesting talk about the state of Microservices, organizational challenges for companies
which want to try and also consultancy work at banks. As we all know, a picture is worth a thousand words, so here are
some tweet highlights from the keynote</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;how big are they&quot; doesn&#39;t matter for <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Microservices?src=hash">#Microservices</a>; what matters is how many you can handle. do you have a plan? <a href="https://twitter.com/boicy">@boicy</a> at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/icwe2016?src=hash">#icwe2016</a></p>&mdash; Erik Wilde (@dret) <a href="https://twitter.com/dret/status/740090382013374465">June 7, 2016</a></blockquote>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">And areas necessary for an organization to excel at before going for <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/microservices?src=hash">#microservices</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ICWE2016?src=hash">#ICWE2016</a>  <a href="https://t.co/g8hr42yctQ">https://t.co/g8hr42yctQ</a></p>&mdash; Tomasz Pluskiewicz (@tpluscode) <a href="https://twitter.com/tpluscode/status/740093263890223104">June 7, 2016</a></blockquote>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&#39;The death of the integration env&#39; predicted by <a href="https://twitter.com/boicy">@boicy</a>. It&#39;s not possible for 100s of <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Microservices?src=hash">#Microservices</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/icwe2016?src=hash">#icwe2016</a> <a href="https://t.co/kgzPEpqa60">pic.twitter.com/kgzPEpqa60</a></p>&mdash; Tomasz Pluskiewicz (@tpluscode) <a href="https://twitter.com/tpluscode/status/740092582609494016">June 7, 2016</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="rest-apis-a-large-scale-analysis-of-compliance-with-principles-and-best-practices">REST APIs: A Large-Scale Analysis of Compliance with Principles and Best Practices</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, this one I didn’t enjoy as much. <a href="https://twitter.com/floriandanielit">Florian Daniel</a> showed their results
of a large scale analysis of mobile data usage around Milan. The team gathered 78 GB worth of data and calculated a number
of metrics like HTTP method usage, media types, user agents and more. An intriguing idea, but without interaction context
it is really hard to come to any conclusions about the “quality” of any single endpoint from REST perspective. Not to mention
that the dataset likely misses any encrypted traffic, which I would expect to be a significant portion. If anything, the
work is an analysis of HTTP protocol usage on the mobile web, but not really REST at all. This is quite evident when you
look closely at some of the metrics, most of which revolve around the URI (eg. presence of underscores, <code>api</code> in path, 
presence of a trailing slash, version in URI). <a href="../../02/rest-misconceptions-1/">I find it very harmful to consider anything specific about URIs a REST
principle and best practice</a>.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">URI practices are so unnecessary. Come to my <a href="https://twitter.com/wsREST">@wsREST</a> talk on Thursday at 12 to hear more <a href="https://twitter.com/floriandanielit">@floriandanielit</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ICWE2016?src=hash">#ICWE2016</a> <a href="https://t.co/bW1tNi14gy">pic.twitter.com/bW1tNi14gy</a></p>&mdash; Tomasz Pluskiewicz (@tpluscode) <a href="https://twitter.com/tpluscode/status/740111148465422336">June 7, 2016</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="benchmarking-web-api-quality">Benchmarking Web API Quality</h3>

<p>A similar presentation followed, in which <a href="https://twitter.com/erikwittern">Erik Wittern</a> presented the results of a daunting benchmarking of a
some popular public APIs including Twitter and Flickr, but also less popular services like police.co.uk. It was very 
entertaining to see how wildly some APIs differ when requested from different regions and at various time of day.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">.<a href="https://twitter.com/erikwittern">@erikwittern</a> is painting a dire picture of Web API availability <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/icwe2016?src=hash">#icwe2016</a> <a href="https://t.co/1UNoTonVWO">pic.twitter.com/1UNoTonVWO</a></p>&mdash; Philipp Leitner (@xLeitix) <a href="https://twitter.com/xLeitix/status/740120861550739456">June 7, 2016</a></blockquote>

<p>Of course one could argue that such comparison is a bit unfair. For example the aforementioned police.co.uk is likely not
intended to work smoothly from Australia but on the other hand it may of interest to someone anywhere on the globe occasionally.
The authors are aware of limitation to their method but rightly point out that it is very important to plan for availability
when designing a public API. Especially that every single tested service showed occasional peaks in latencies and even 
outages.</p>

<h3 id="mira-a-model-driven-framework-for-semantic-interfaces-for-web-applications">MIRA: A Model-Driven Framework for Semantic Interfaces for Web Applications</h3>

<p>Next presentation that really got my attention was <a href="https://twitter.com/SchwabeD">Daniel Schwabe’s</a> presentation of <a href="https://github.com/TecWebLab/mira">MIRA</a>, a JavaScript tool
and RDF notation for modelling user interfaces with abstract elements, so that they can be replaced by concrete elements
on a given platform. This method addresses the volatility of the web and the shortcoming of responsive design, which will
soon be unable to cater for futuristic User Interfaces.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">These are four reasons why responsive web design isn&#39;t enough. Talk by <a href="https://twitter.com/SchwabeD">@schwabed</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ICWE2016?src=hash">#ICWE2016</a> <a href="https://t.co/XuJIGz3lXt">pic.twitter.com/XuJIGz3lXt</a></p>&mdash; Tomasz Pluskiewicz (@tpluscode) <a href="https://twitter.com/tpluscode/status/740152809941827584">June 7, 2016</a></blockquote>

<p>MIRA authors also boast their results which show that for seasoned programmers and non-developers alike it took the least
time to build a simple application using their tool. However we’ve seen that already, which makes me skeptical (I’m looking
at you Lightswitch!).</p>

<p>There is a demo available at <a href="http://mira.tecweb.inf.puc-rio.br/">http://mira.tecweb.inf.puc-rio.br/</a>.</p>

<h3 id="volatile-functionality-in-action-methods-techniques-and-assessmenthttpicwe2016infusichsitesicwe2016filesslidesdarian-frajbergpptx"><a href="http://icwe2016.inf.usi.ch/sites/icwe2016/files/slides/Darian-Frajberg.pptx">Volatile Functionality in Action: Methods, Techniques and Assessment</a></h3>

<p>This was another slight disappointment of that day. Darian Frajberg presented their evaluation of using various techniques
to manage volatile functionalities of an application. An example is a time-limited prices reduction on certain item on an
e-commerce platform. The problem there is that programming tools such as code weaving and regular expressions, which were
the basis for their platform are very demanding on the programmers. Even when packaged as a reusable library, such a library
would take a great effort to support and evolve. Also, the authors didn’t really compare their results to real methods
used in practice. The baseline for their evaluation included naïve and unrealistice methods, which would not be used in
serious software.</p>

<h3 id="abstracting-and-structuring-web-contents-for-supporting-personal-web-experiencehttpicwe2016infusichsitesicwe2016filesslidesgabriela-bosettiwoapdf"><a href="http://icwe2016.inf.usi.ch/sites/icwe2016/files/slides/Gabriela-Bosetti_WOA.pdf">Abstracting and Structuring Web contents for supporting Personal Web Experience</a></h3>

<p>This very unassuming and slightly misleading title hides an exciting piece of software called <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/webobjectambient">Web Objects Ambient</a>.
It is a Firefox extension (with a Chrome version a possibility) which allows end users to enhance web content by interacting
with elements and combining it with more data like tweets, reviews, etc. And it uses DBpedia as the source of concepts <img class="emoji" title=":+1:" alt=":+1:" src="https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f44d.png" height="20" width="20" align="absmiddle" />.
In case I somehow failed to convey the general idea, here’s a video showing WOA in action.</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kZyHZpU8ue8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Finally, there is also an <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/webobjectambient/documentation">extensibility model</a>, which allows
developers to extend the sidebar seen above with more powers!</p>

<h3 id="the-direwolf-inside-you-end-user-development-for-heterogeneous-web-of-things-applianceshttpwwwslidesharenetistvankorenthe-direwolf-inside-you-end-user-development-for-heterogeneous-web-of-things-appliances"><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/IstvanKoren/the-direwolf-inside-you-end-user-development-for-heterogeneous-web-of-things-appliances">The DireWolf Inside You: End User Development for Heterogeneous Web of Things Appliances</a></h3>

<p>Because RDF Streams are above me I’m skipping right to the last presentation of the day. Awarded the Best Vision Paper Award,
the vision by <a href="https://twitter.com/istinhere">Istvan Koren</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/klamma">Ralf Klamma</a> ongoing effort to build a distributed End User Interface for
the Web of Things. Build with Polymer and their own peer-to-peer communication library! Again, because a picture will
explain uch better than words, here the slide showing an overview of the authors’ vision.</p>

<p><a href="/uploads/2016/06/direwolf_big.png"><img src="/uploads/2016/06/direwolf.png" alt="DireWolf overview slide" /></a></p>

<script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lest I forget&#58; International Conference on Web Engineering - Day 1 Research Tracks]]></title>
    <link href="http://t-code.pl/blog/2016/06/ICWE-2016-day-1/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-13T22:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://t-code.pl/blog/2016/06/ICWE-2016-day-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past week I took part in the <a href="http://icwe2016.inf.usi.ch">International Conference on Web Engineering</a> or ICWE for
short. I’d like to round up the lectures I attended, demos I watched and posters I saw. While I still remember, I want to
write about my impressions about each individual one, at least at the very shortest. Of course I won’t be able to cover
it all, because I wasn’t able to attend every session for obvious reasons and at the same time I didn’t find everything
equally interesting. I’ll do my best nonetheless.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="day-1">Day 1</h2>

<p>Throughout the three conference days I mostly attended the Research Tracks. They contain a whole lot of knowledge, new ideas
and ingenious tools. Here’s what caught my attention on the first day.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/2016/06/icwe-program.jpg" alt="icwe program cover" /></p>

<h3 id="the-keynote---quo-vadis-google-knowledge-graph">The keynote - Quo vadis Google Knowledge Graph</h3>

<p>The conference started with a <a href="http://icwe2016.inf.usi.ch/program/keynotes/xin.luna.dong">talk</a> by <a href="http://lunadong.com/">Xin Luna Dong</a>
about the Google Knowledge Graph. It was very interesting to see how Google employs a data model similar in concept to
RDF to build it’s massive knowledge base, how Freebase is currently being replaced by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge_Vault">Google Knowledge Vault</a> and
learn about (Lightweight) Verticals, which are one how Google collects its data. However, as one listener points out:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ICWE2016?src=hash">#ICWE2016</a>! Nice presentation by Luna Dong but... where is Wikidata?</p>&mdash; Alberto Tonon (@otreblanonot) <a href="https://twitter.com/otreblanonot/status/739729514750742529">June 6, 2016</a></blockquote>

<h3 id="ctat-tilt-and-tap-across-devices">CTAT: Tilt-and-Tap Across Devices</h3>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Thank you really much <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/icwe2016?src=hash">#icwe2016</a> for this award.Special thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/mariahusman">@MariaHusman</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Abhi?src=hash">#Abhi</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/can?src=hash">#can</a>  and my mentor <a href="https://twitter.com/emseen">@emseen</a>. <a href="https://t.co/q4PI4otfHM">pic.twitter.com/q4PI4otfHM</a></p>&mdash; Lindig (@lindadigeronimo) <a href="https://twitter.com/lindadigeronimo/status/740461345632620544">June 8, 2016</a></blockquote>

<p>This interesting work by <a href="https://twitter.com/lindadigeronimo">Linda Di Geronimo</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/MariaHusmann">Maria Husmann</a>, Abhimanyu Patel, Can Tuerk and <a href="https://twitter.com/emseen">Moira C. Norrie</a>
was awarded the Best Paper Award for good reason. During the talk we could watch what great interactions can be achieve
by communicating multiple mobile device equipped with accelerometers. That has some proper SCI-FI potential. And just thing
about all the games. Well, unfortunately we’ve heard that lagging would be too great for dynamic real-time interaction, 
but some less intensive activities? After all we all have a universal Wii-like controller in our pockets. It just so happens
that it can take calls.</p>

<p><video width='870' preload='metadata' controls ><source src='/uploads/2016/06/ctat.mp4' type='video/mp4; codecs="avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2"'></video></p>

<h3 id="revisting-web-data-extraction-using-in-browser-structural-analysis-and-visual-cues-in-modern-web-designs">Revisting Web Data Extraction using In-Browser Structural Analysis and Visual Cues in Modern Web Designs</h3>

<p>In his presentation, <a href="https://twitter.com/alfonsomurolo">Alfonso Murolo</a> showcased his Chrome extension called <strong>DeepDesign</strong>, which uses some 
state-of-the-art techniques to aid extracting (scraping) data from websites. The extension takes advantage of structural
and visual cues to automate the creation of wrappers for extracting data from web pages. I only wish that the extension
was made public and included a crawler so that entire websites can be scraped. Currently it requires manual action.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">DeepDesign: Chrome Web extractor extension. I was looking for this! Will have to try it out. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ICWE2016?src=hash">#ICWE2016</a> <a href="https://t.co/8e74pJct1D">pic.twitter.com/8e74pJct1D</a></p>&mdash; Tomasz Pluskiewicz (@tpluscode) <a href="https://twitter.com/tpluscode/status/739754809729929216">June 6, 2016</a></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately, currently trying DeepDesign won’t be possible.</p>

<h3 id="clustering-aided-page-object-generation-for-web-testing">Clustering-Aided Page Object Generation for Web Testing</h3>

<p>First day, and yet another award - for best student paper. In this presentation the audience was introduced to <a href="http://sepl.dibris.unige.it/APOGEN.php">APOGEN</a> 
or <strong>Automatic Page Objects Generator</strong>. It is a Java tool, which crawls a website to create Page Objects for its pages.
However it does by combining multiple instances of the same page into clusters. It allows correcting these clusters with
a simple UI. That UI even shows small renderings of crawled pages. There is so much usefulness in this tool and it is
already <a href="https://app.assembla.com/spaces/sepl-apo/subversion/source/HEAD/trunk">available as open source</a> (just why SVN?).</p>

<p><video width='870' preload='metadata' controls poster='/uploads/2016/06/apogen.png'><source src='/uploads/2016/06/apogen.mp4' type='video/mp4; codecs="avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2"'></video></p>

<p>How cool is that? If I ever hear that scientific conferences don’t have anything practical offer to I will slap that
person across their face <img class="emoji" title=":wink:" alt=":wink:" src="https://assets.github.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/1f609.png" height="20" width="20" align="absmiddle" />.</p>

<h3 id="qwwwq-querying-wikipedia-without-writing-queries">QwwwQ: Querying Wikipedia without writing queries</h3>

<p>This is another cool Chrome extension I’m very excited about, which unfortunately is not available publicly just yet.
QwwwQ (pron. quick) is an ingenious tool for querying <a href="http://dbpedia.org">DBpedia</a> in a way I would describe as a mix of
query-by-example and maybe faceted search. It would allow non-technical users to explore the wealth of data stored on
wikipedia and also help developers build SPARQL queries for DBpedia with a nice GUI instead of a text editor. In their
paper the authors (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/massimiliano-battan-2b49b359">Massimiliano Battan</a> and <a href="http://latemar.science.unitn.it/segue/index.php?&amp;login=logout&amp;action=site&amp;site=ronchet">Marco Ronchetti</a>) mention future plans for allowing <code>JOIN</code>
operations to traverse relations. I would add to that list the possibility to retrieve the underlying query for further
customization.</p>

<p>What I found most interesting is that QwwwQ cites a 1975 paper <em>A psychological study of query by example</em> by John C. Thomas
and John D. Gould. Isn’t that cool?</p>

<h3 id="aspect-based-sentiment-analysis-on-the-web-using-rhetorical-structure-theory">Aspect-Based Sentiment Analysis on the Web using Rhetorical Structure Theory</h3>

<p>Another award that day - Distinguished Paper Award. Although the topic is quite advanced, the presenters succinctly explained
their application of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhetorical_Structure_Theory">Rhetorical Structure Theory or RST</a> in
deriving sentiment from product reviews written in English. What does it mean? It means that by deconstructing and
classifying parts of a review multiple algorithms devised by the authors can determine what positive and negative sentiments
the reviewer expressed. Interestingly, the results are slightly worse for negative reviews (allegedly, because positive 
words are often used to express negative sentiments) and results are better for reviews consisting of multiple sentences.</p>

<h3 id="diversity-in-social-media-urban-analytics">Diversity in Social Media Urban Analytics</h3>

<p>An fairly interesting paper, which shows how social media activity data (from Twitter and Instagram in this case) can be
used to determine patterns of their respective users in cities. The authors analyzed the usage of said social networks in
four European cities: Amsterdam, London, Paris and Rome. Among the findings the authors discovered that</p>

<ul>
  <li>Instagram users concentrate more in the vicinity of tourist locations</li>
  <li>The same can be said for tourists as opposed to residents</li>
  <li>Instagram shows more uniform activity over time in various cities that Twitter (for example Amsterdam Twitter activity dies out much quicker in evenings)</li>
  <li>Both social networks’ activity is proportional to city size</li>
  <li>The activity of people aged 45+ is very low</li>
</ul>

<p>As unsurprising as they may seem, these results are not really meant to reflect the reality in 100%. The authors are aware
of the challenges and acknowledge shortcomings of their techniques. This paper is however a good exploration of various
possibilities which await a data scientist who is interested in analyzing social behaviour on the web.</p>

<h3 id="design-of-cqa-systems-for-flexible-and-scalable-deployment-and-evaluationhttpicwe2016infusichsitesicwe2016filesslidesivan-srbapdf"><a href="http://icwe2016.inf.usi.ch/sites/icwe2016/files/slides/Ivan-Srba.pdf">Design of CQA Systems for Flexible and Scalable Deployment and Evaluation</a></h3>

<p>Another work with so much potential for practical application. Long ago I have been looking for a good, open source
alternative to Stack Exchange. It turns out that there is one such open-source project being developed at Slovak University
of Technology in Bratislava. Its focus is on educational use and has unique features for teachers/students and integrates
with edX and MOOC. It is also used on the University in Lugano.</p>

<p>Oh, and did I mention that it is open source and <a href="https://github.com/AskalotCQA/askalot">hosted on GitHub</a>? Go give it a
try.</p>

<script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
